喂，係。
林庭慧先生，民主黨。
噉就我舉一個好簡單嘅例子，噉就係。
噉佢哋如果想去買樓啊，可能真係靠負幹嘅啫。
住户其實就係講緊家庭住户入邊所有成員都係十八至廿九歲嘅誒年青人。
一個咧公屋長大嘅年青人，可能月入一萬幾蚊，申請公屋已經係冇乜可能㗎啦。咁申請呢個居屋又未必供得起，私樓就更加唔使諗啦。噉樣。
誒，主席，我係民主黨社區主任林庭偉啦。噉我今日想講嘅係青年貧窮嗰個問題。誒，咁因為咧，青年就未必係最窮嗰一班人啊，不過咧就一定係最畀人忽視嗰一班。
啊！咁大家可能話啊，咁都覺得奇怪喎，點解係十八至廿九咧？咁因為喺誒呢個年頭到底有幾多嘅年輕人係可以誒自己出嚟住咧，或者係同其他青年人合租咧噉樣？
一國三帶嘅情況下，到底佢呢個報告係咪真係反映到我哋香港啊係有幾多嘅青年貧窮咧？有幾多嘅貧窮嘅青年咧？噉樣即係我哋都想反映翻，即係其實個報告係反映到唔唔到依家嗰個真實個情況。
未攞到嘅話咧，我哋嘅保安同事咧可以畀你嘅。咁咧就今日發言以以外咧，你哋如果有誒任何嘅誒意見書咧，都可以喺今日同埋之後咧補發畀我哋嘅，補交畀我哋嘅。OK，咁咧就誒我哋今日要找緊時間啦，啊，咁咧就誒開始啦，誒先請。
正式開始，咁咧就歡迎咧第二節嘅朋友啦嚇。呢一節嘅時間咧係十一點十分至到一點鐘嘅。咁共總共咧有三十一個團體咧係報咗名出席。咁咧就誒，請大家留意啦。咁咧就我哋嘅擴音擴音器咧同埋耳筒咧，零號咧就係現場版，一號係廣東話，二號英文，三號咧就係普通。
話噉，大家咧可以帶上嚟普通話。我哋有，我哋我帶動耳筒咧，我哋會有即時嘅翻譯嘅。咁而我哋今日咧嗰個誒發言嘅次序咧，就跟大家嘅座位啊、啊座位已經安排咗。今日咧亦都有一啲旁聽嘅朋友啦。咁再提醒大家誒旁聽咧同同埋出席嘅都一樣咧，你嘅發言咧係唔受到咧係。
特立法會特權入權力及特權條例三百八十二章所定嘅保障同埋豁免嘅，同時間咧，你哋所提交嘅意見書咧，係唔會受到該條例嘅保障同埋豁免嘅，所以咧即係話咧係嚴責自負嘅。咁旁聽嘅朋友咧，亦都有一個公眾人士須知，請大家留意。咁咧，如果你誒未攞未睇到嘅話，
因為根據咧2017年香港貧窮情況報告咧，就話香港咧2017年喺政策介入之前咧，嗰個青年貧窮住户有五千八百人，喺介入咗之後咧就減到去三千九，噉啊可能對比起報告入邊咧，誒其他類別人士可能真係誒微不足道嘅。不過咧喺呢個報告入邊咧就話嗰個青年。
好，真係完最快完成。
越嚴重啊！嚇，噉我哋都睇到。
受到任何嘅即係社會保障噉樣。
咧去做一個貸款，咁學資處嗰個資料顯示，就一六一七年咧。
過去嗰十年咧，香港嘅堅尼係數咧都係維持喺零點五三幾嘅，噉係比好多嘅發展國家都仲要高。
四萬一千五百六十人就獲批咗呢個貸款嘅，咁一七一八年都有三萬三千九百一十五就批咗，即係話呢班學生仔咧未出嚟做嘢，已已經係咧誒有一筆好大嘅負債喺度。
今日嘅發言咧，主要係評論誒現時嘅貧窮計算方法。噉，我認為就係用貧窮線作為量度貧窮嘅誒工具咧，係唔足以反映貧窮人口嗰個生活狀況，亦都未能為香港滅貧咧提供一個具體嘅目標。
咁再睇翻，可能一四去到一七年啦。咁有關嗰個香港青年住屋嗰個抽樣調查咧，十八去到三十四歲嗰啲後生仔咧，有八成都係同父母住嘅，即係話講緊可能有兩有七個percent啦，都係獨居或者係同伴侶住嘅啫。咁喺香港呢個咧百物騰貴，自己住又～
咁而家啲後生仔咧，可能要結婚、誒置業、生仔啦，進修都係一個經濟考量嚟嘅。咁可能隨住呢個專上教育普及化啦，可能個個都覺得啊，讀大學都係一個誒揾工嘅一個入場券嚟嘅。但係問題往往就係咧，誒依家讀大學都係需要錢嘅。咁好多後誒年輕人都係需要。
所以而家咧啲後生仔可能咧誒，可能係唯有係靠富幹啦，即係有家庭內部嘅財富轉移啦，或者係成功置業，同時帶嚟一個嘅資產升值，加強咗呢個社會階級地位嘅噉樣。咁如果同冇我哋冇富幹嘅年青人比咧，個差距越拉越大，貧富懸殊嘅情況咧都越嚟。
係啦，咁睇到咧，而家嗰個誒後生誒貧窮一代啊，嗰啲後生仔咧冇乜上流機會，輸喺起跑線上邊。咁想靠呢個命運去改變知識改變命運咧，亦都係需要有一個負債喺度。所以咧，呢個往往就係我哋香港人而家嘅苦況。噉啊，都希望咧，大家都關注翻青年貧窮。
誒嗰個真實情況問題，多謝主席。好唔該曬誒，原來成功教靠父幹個學術名稱叫做家庭內部財政轉移啊。咁呢個我今日都學到嘢，多謝你。跟住請誒民主青年李永賢小姐。好多謝主席，我係民主黨社區主任李永賢。噉我今
咁貧窮線咧係用一個即係相對貧窮嘅概念啦。噉就係以即係政策介入之前，按照唔同嘅住户人數嘅收入中位數嘅五十percent定呢個貧窮線嘅。咁所以貧窮線以下就係貧窮人口。咁但係好可惜，香港嘅誒貧富懸殊咧嘅差距係好大。
咁堅尼係數大咧，代表住一個社會嘅兩極化嘅情況好嚴重啦。咁所以依個係即係對數字上對貧窮嘅理解，但係其實相對貧窮咧，亦都係顯示咗有同冇，咁亦都係代表住有啲人有特權、有機會，但係有啲人就乜都冇。
係被削弱嘅一羣咁喺英國咧，好多時都會將貧窮啦，即係poverty同埋社會排外social exclusion呢兩個概念咧，係攞埋一齊嚟去研究嘅。咁亦都有學者會提到點解有啲人會越越有錢咧？咁尤其是當一個地區佢誒有錢嘅。
嘅人十個percent係佔咗成個地區大部分嘅GDP，依一個咧唔係一個即係仇富嘅論説，而係反映咗制度上嘅唔公平，噉係政府保護唔到誒社會上弱勢嘅人，咁所以好似香港噉樣啦嘅勞工保障啦，或者家庭主婦啊、照顧者依啲都係冇。
咁究竟香港嘅貧窮人口係咪就係得嗰一百三十幾萬咧？咁其實貧窮除咗係代表即係金錢嘅缺乏咧，亦都包含住市民咧嘅生活同埋健康質素咧，能唔能夠達到即係誒社會普遍嘅標準嘅？所以我建議，除咗喺誒依個。
個貧窮線依個計算方法咧，亦都要有其他工具去評估誒，即係貧窮嘅多面性啦。咁其實二零一四年咧，中大同埋誒社聯都做過依方面嘅研究嘅，噉就係以多項嘅基本生活需要咧作為指標。咁譬如問受訪者佢哋每一日能唔能夠食。
講嘅人口較高嘅。
少數族咧，尤其係南亞裔嘅人口咧，比較係誒年輕嘅。咁政府咧應該係更加需要為呢一啲香港嘅新一代咧係提供支援，去提升咧未來整體人力資源嘅質素。
家庭因為可能普遍較大啦，縱使咧係在職咧，都係唔能夠脱貧。咁中文能力咧嘅教信息咧，都係影響咗佢哋升讀專上教育啦、就業能力啦，同埋融入社會嘅主要障礙。
Good morning, everyone. I am Ruby Aslam. I am here to be a medical engineering student at the City University of Hong Kong. Today, I want to discuss the post-secondary education choices available for non-Chinese speaking students in Hong Kong.
平等嘅教育嘅畀到呢個少數族裔咧，好多少數族裔而家就算係讀咗十二年，以至話係讀埋幼稚園啦、十五年啦，佢哋學到嘅中文程度咧，只係得一個小二嘅中文程度。噉你點樣叫佢出嚟揾工，或者更加係去誒讀一個專上嘅課程咧？
到健康嘅誒，即係嘅生果啊、蔬菜噉樣，或者每個月佢哋能唔能夠出外同家人去參與一啲活動？呢啲咧都係好具體化咁去評估香港貧窮嘅情況。同時，即使係高於貧窮線嘅人咧，佢哋嘅生活質素都可能係好差嘅。噉我希望除咗政府誒會加。
啊！依個即係資源之外咧，亦都要有針對性嘅政策同埋目標，先至能夠惠及誒有需要嘅市民。多謝好，唔該曬。跟住請Miss Felix張，多謝主席。誒，我係誒Felix，係香港融樂會嘅。咁根據二零一六年嘅誒人口普查咧，少數族裔其實佔香港。
嘅人口咧唔多嘅，只係誒百分之四嘅啫。但係咧，少數族裔咧有三高嘅，咁有邊三樣高咧？係佢哋咧係都係個比率咧係比全港嘅人口高。第一就係誒佢哋未有機會去就讀專上教育啦，佢哋嘅誒貧窮率啦，同埋佢哋嘅在職貧窮咧，都係比全港。
咁喺在職貧窮咧，如我哋就睇到誒二零一四年同埋一六年嘅誒少數族裔人士嘅貧窮報告咧，都有講到佢哋係以在職貧窮為主，但係咧同整體嘅貧窮情況咧係唔同嘅。噉佢哋在職貧窮嘅原因咧，係因為在職嘅人士學歷啦，同埋佢嘅技能咧係較遜色。
咁如果我哋睇緊，政委都有講啦，十四至廿四歲嗰個誒人口咧，其實佢哋比起誒一般嘅人咧，係低於十一個，即係比誒比起全港咧係低低低十一個百分點，有機會去讀一啲專上嘅教育㗎。咁所以佢哋就業嘅收入咧水平就比較低，通常咧加。
咁誒，其實大家都知道啦，教育咧係減少跨代貧窮嘅主要途徑。但係我就好奇怪，點解今日全日裏邊嘅公聽會咧，竟然冇教育局出現嘅？咁同埋容樂會都講咗好多次㗎啦。其實好教育局幾時先至可以醒？佢真係畀一個誒有一個。
係。
They use Chinese to interview candidates.
Miss Cam Camille Camille Pick。
only 50% of the programmes are available.
Unfortunately， we are not the norm， though we wish we are。
Present planning on post-secondary education in Hong Kong has overlooked the needs of non-Chinese-speaking students. Thank you. Thank you.
To be honest, I personally believe that such barriers are making these programmes nearly inaccessible to non-Chinese-speaking students.
although many of the ethnic minority speakers sitting here today are university students, please don't take this to mean that there is nothing wrong with the policies.
There is an uneven implementation of the alternative Chinese qualification, and government really needs to examine courses or programs with unreasonable Chinese requirements that effectively preclude EM from applying.
most of our classmates are motivated to study further, but since there is an achievement gap between EM and Chinese students due to poor education policies, and since poverty report pointed out that EM have lower education attainment.
咁誒，我哋希望咧，其實教育局咧係應該針對翻而家有冇一個中文為第二語言嘅一個政策，咁由幼轉開始，利用呢一個正確嘅方法，可以教到佢哋中文，等到佢哋可以咧係涵接入去主流嘅中文嗰度。咁最緊要咧就係要有一個有階段性嘅學習目標啦。而家呢一
一個嘅架構咧係冇嘅，咁同埋一定要有一個師資嘅培訓，咁學前同埋管理層咧，亦都係應該受到咧多元化嘅培訓，去推展校園嘅共融環境。咁呢一個唔即係中文能力低咧，唔單單止咧係對於接受專上教育啊揾到一份好工，其實咧係令到佢哋瞭解子女嘅。
嘅教育啊，社區參與啊，都係好大嘅影響。咁其實容樂會呢度咧，期望政務司司長帶領嘅少數族裔事務督導委員會咧，會針對呢一啲觀察作出一啲唔係講緊扶貧啊，喺啲預防誒貧窮嘅措施，特別喺教育方面著墨。多謝主席，唔該曬Miss Ruby啊。
Despite the government's claim that non-Chinese speaking students can choose their education paths according to their interest and Chinese language abilities, many ethnic minority youths are still facing barriers in accessing post-secondary education because of the language barrier and many other reasons.
In addition to this, according to a research conducted by the Hong Kong Unison, it has been found out that some programmes use Chinese as the medium of instructions. Have compulsory courses taught in Chinese do not accept alternative Chinese language qualifications, and even the
Moreover, the government claimed in 2014 policy address that non-Chinese speaking students may pursue different pathways according to their aspirations and Chinese proficiency, but in reality, students have very limited choices. For instance, when programmes medium of instruction
Interview language and accommodations on Chinese compulsory courses were analysed. Seventy-one per cent of all secondary courses are not suitable for students who do not speak nor write Chinese, and for students who can speak but cannot write Chinese.
which is basically linked to their income level and how ethnic minorities are stuck at low-skilled jobs. The government should review the post-secondary education progression ladder to better suit the needs of non-Chinese-speaking students. The government really needs to re-examine its EDB policies because.
Good morning, everyone. My name is Kamalpreet Kaur and I'm an Year 2 university student in Hong Kong. What I want to highlight today is the ambiguity and irony of this notion of the standard family size, which is emphasised repetitively in the government's reports of the poverty situation of ethnic minorities, especially South Asian minorities.
to begin with, the Hong Kong poverty situation report on ethnic minorities from two thousand and sixteen makes a very interesting remark. It basically summarises the average household size of ethnic minorities and conveniently compares it to that of the general population. It notes that the average South Asian household size was three zero persons, while
miss阿玲。
政府唔應該 aim 到單出南亞家庭的大小作為他們困境的主要原因。
如果系統不設 cater to large family household sizes，，則這係一個關鍵的缺點喺個系統。
因為 no household size should be too large to be supported and to be able to live at a dignified quality of life.
和預測的勞動短缺，，一個批評，，一個大型家庭規模，是 not only mind-boggling， but also very ironic。
after all, poverty is not a choice of the South Asian minority. It is a consequence of a system that is failing to support them. Thank you for your time. Thank you.
當你 step out of facts and numbers and really think about it， which household size average is more abnormal？ The household with an average of two. point seven persons or that with three. point zero persons？
The way the Chinese curriculum has been handled has played a part. It has sowed a seed of doubt in most EM students that they have lost the fight before it has even begun, and here's how it has done it.
因為在做噉樣，它亦都暗示著貧窮的南亞少數民族，例如印度人、巴基斯坦人和那不勒斯人，是自食其果，他們係因為有更多嘅孩子，所以佢哋應該要留在佢哋嘅困境。
my name is Rui Arlen L, a local Nepali student currently studying at the University of Hong Kong. My ethnic group has the highest dropout rate of more than 20% in high school. I'm one of the few that became the exception to that.
by making them realise they lack the language that will so profusely affect their career choices. But what waters these doubts further are the way E.M. students are treated by their teachers, teachers who fail to help us gain the confidence to see further beyond our disadvantage.
就業和福利服務對於ethnic minorities是失敗，未能支持和社會動員ethnic minorities。或許，這個系統應該被嚴格重新考慮，因為它是失敗未能支持大型家庭規模的ethnic minorities。
Surely we cannot trudge off this matter by saying that most M kids are lazy, do not have the ability or the capability to pursue tertiary education, because we sit here as proof before you that we are more than capable of pursuing it. So there must be something deeper than that.
而那，which was larger than that of the average of all household sizes, which was 2.7 persons. As a first glance, this may seem to be a legible point contributing to the poverty of South Asian households in Hong Kong. But when you consider the context of this report to be about Hong Kong, the city that is facing a dire ageing pop,
really the government should be aiming to support all households regardless of size despite one working household member if nineteen percent of South Asian households generally remain in poverty as is cited in the same report from two thousand and sixteen then the problem is in the system the fact of the matter is that the government policies in education
and now I'm seen as a beacon of hope, inspiration and a role model, all because I'm going to university. How crazy does that sound? That's simply because I'm pursuing a tertiary education, something that should be completely normal. I became someone extraordinary. This happened because I'm not the norm here in Hong Kong.
For my community, and I can say that with the utmost confidence, as you have heard just a speaker ago say, that we are not the norm at all, and that should not be the case. So where have we gone wrong as a city that scores extremely well on Programme for International Student Assessment, also known as PISA, a city tagged as exam?
different。
啊！
Thank you, Annie. Miss Hina, please.
then we need to start supporting them completely. Thank you, chairperson.
definitely apply to VTC or community colleges for sure. All these comments, which such pessimistic outlooks on our future academic
which university would you like to go to? A question that should be asked is never asked to most EM kids because we are already assumed to have failed. Even I was never asked that in my high school. Instead, I've heard and have been told by so many students that their teachers have told them you'll never get to university.
on our academic future are said because the teachers are reflecting the trend in their actions and the words. It doesn't happen in a school. It happens in a lot of schools. So if we want to stop this, we've got to start training our teachers to be more culturally sensitive. We need to start focusing on training the teachers to understand the needs of these students who often
feel alienated and uncared for in a place where they spend most of their youth. As much as teachers need to be trained for special needs students, because so do they for EM students. Because the fact that they're culturally different makes their needs different, and you cannot cater to someone you have no idea about. I have been asked this question: how
我教EM kids， and now as absurd as that sounds， as we were another species， it shows the lack of exposure these teachers in training have had， and again highlights the importance of training these teachers officially。所以，如果我們要訓練EM學生，如果我們要EM學生開始得到更高的教育成就，我們需要。
My name is Bashirina, a Hong Kong Pakistani. We are aware of the fact that education, specifically Chinese language, is the key to ethnic minorities' integration into the community, finding a stable job and even admission to post-secondary or tertiary education. Despite of being called a local student and local citizen, ethnic minorities are deprived of rights to equitable quality.
教育，EDB has introduced the Chinese learning curriculum second language learning framework for non-Chinese speaking students. But many students have found the curriculum easy or meaningless. The main point is why does EDB preset low objectives for ethnic minorities when it comes to Chinese learning in comparison to Chinese local? We are told Chinese is objectively hard.
hard to learn. So here's a simpler version and easier curriculum for you. Instead of encouraging us to aim for higher proficiency, we are told to adopt an alternative easy curriculum. And after studying the easy curriculum with little or zero proficiency in Chinese, how can we land on the same employment opportunities? The government is setting us up for failure. During the beginning of my
我 life，我 took the initiative to take local Chinese curriculum instead，因為我 knew how important picking up the language was in every aspect of life，whether it be been working or socialising。Nevertheless，我 was told to switch to an easier Chinese curriculum for the sake of comfort for the entirety of my school life。我 was told it will be difficult for you to adapt and learn。During G。
GCSE exams and taking APL Chinese courses are of little avail. Chinese curriculums like GCSE for secondary students are equivalent to primary one or two Chinese level in a local primary school, where we learn very basic Cantonese words. Chinese being called hard becomes an obstacle from us, which from my perspective is very misleading. I've also
Witness my learning curve deteriorating. Also, according to Hong Kong Poverty Situation Report on Ethnic Minorities in 2016, larger proportion of EMs aged five and above claim ability to speak English than to speak Chinese. For many, English isn't our first language or mother tongue. Yet we manage to be proficient. Then how is learning Cantonese any?
and.
講緊關於一個大學。
Miss胡頌詩。
for teachers who have received professional training in teaching Chinese as second language.
C.S.L. education policy, which well supports Chinese learning. Thank you. Thank you.
to their learning needs, nor assisted teachers in formulating effective learning strategies.
my name is Umikultsum Ahter and I am a student from HKU studying Bachelor of Nursing.
Today I will be talking about two things. First of all, the teachers' training on the framework of learning Chinese as a second language, and then cultural sensitivity among them.
那係也係一個原因，為甚麼我學了同班同學一樣的中一課程，但係我唔能夠考到一半，因為我係一個弱勢學生。
Even with my teachers and my own best effort, at the end of the day, I still had to sit GCE. Now there are two problems that need to be highlighted here. First of all, there is no teachers' training to teach Cantonese as a second language.
Studying in a local mainstream secondary school, I got to see the problem first hand. For my first four years of Chinese learning, I learned Cantonese sitting together with local Chinese students. But what has continuously been ignored is that learning a native language and a second language is not the same.
When someone is learning a second language, they have to be taught from the very basics of it, such as the vocabulary and tenses, on which to base the rest of their knowledge from the syllabus. However, till now, the government has not provided teachers with training, a standardised curriculum for teaching non-Chinese students.
The policy goal of the learning framework was originally to help non-Chinese speaking students bridge over to mainstream Chinese curriculum, and the EDB said the framework will be reviewed every three years. However, now in the fifth year of the implementation of the framework, the government has yet to make the report available to stakeholders. The government should immediately.
Chinese as second language policy with stage learning objectives, coupled with suitable teaching methods to teach students whose mother tongue is not Chinese, so that their learning ability and Chinese ability can reach similar levels as their Chinese peers. I believe we ethnic minorities should be entitled to quality, equitable education, and the EDB should restructure.
Now we appreciate that the government has started to recognise the difficulties faced by ethnic minorities in Cantonese learning, but what is frustrating is the fact that the government thinks that it can use money alone to solve this problem. The government has poured money into the Chinese as second language learning framework for non-Chinese students, but it has not fully responded.
What needs to be done is that the EDB should take a more active role in formulating a long-term education policy for teaching Cantonese to ethnic minority students. The authorities should also provide adequate and systematic systematic training opportunities and incentives for prospective teachers, in-service teachers and schools, and consider raising salary points.
secondly, the government needs to do more to raise awareness about teachers' awareness about cultural sensitivity. I learned from my colleague who is currently undertaking her degree in education at HKU that future teachers are not taught cultural sensitivity as a core module, and the graphs would be similar in other universities. We are.
Thank you.
Good morning. My name is Muhammad Rohail. Pakistani born and raised in Hong Kong.
having gone through the local education system here from a kindergarten with lots of non-Chinese students.
SE， there are only 100 students sitting for HKDSE Chinese every year.
啊，thank you very much。誒，我哋覺得係得。啊，the next one is how.
Learning Cantonese and to be able to better assist them during the learning process. Thank you, Chairperson. Thank you, Ms. Iwach.
或The requirements are something that you cannot fit in. Again, where is the loophole? The Hong Kong government sets the standards really low for ethnic minorities in primary and secondary schools regarding the Chinese subject.
寫字和寫字要求適當的正式訓練。 last but not the least, if we are not thought Chinese well, it affects our further education and employment opportunities, and it will affect the long term quality of of the life of us and our children. Thank you.
That's that ranks fifth in the world and has a large percentage of international and non non Chinese local students. It is very important to increase cultural sensitivity of teachers in designated schools with ethnic minority students, in order for the teachers to be able to understand the difficulty faced by ethnic minority kids.
Good morning, everyone. My name is Ikra, a Year Four student studying at HKU. Why does poverty exist? Why do ethnic minorities or youngsters have to go for low-income jobs? Factors are the opportunities some are provided with. Either they do not have options to choose from because of the language barrier some might face in the work.
I know many people and have a few classmates whom Chinese is not even at fundamental level, and I wonder why. It is all due to the reason of what have been taught to them throughout their primary and secondary level. Referring back to the number of NCS students sitting for the internationally recognised alternative Chinese language qualifications examinations.
which are GCSE, IGCSE, GCE Chinese and the last few years provided by the government. One very obvious fact is that the numbers have been increasing, indicating that students are meant to be taught for these levels in their schools respectively. Each year, amount about 1,000 NCS students taking.
only around thirty people, which is three percent of all the NCS students, can obtain a level three or above, which is the general entrance requirement for UGC programmes. Compared to the figure of fifty six percent of overall student population being able to achieve the same result, there is obviously a huge disparity.
which can only be attributed to the failure of the system to provide Chinese as a second language curriculum, but not the personal effort of students and teachers. At the same time, we also have to face the stereotype that many Chinese people have for us in Hong Kong, including including the teachers thinking that we do not have the ability and are not capable.
Of learning Chinese, but think this way: English was also a new language for us. Shouldn't be shouldn't Chinese be easier for us to catch up with, given the fact that the environment we are surrounded by? Them guys they got to them take provide us with the opportunity first. We can learn English because we are taught English as a second language.
I think if we are thought Chinese with similar method, we can do pretty well. All I would say from my experience is that the spoken of many South Asians is way better than reading and writing ability. Why? Because people can catch, pick up speaking and listening aspect of a language through the environmental exposure, but reading.
specifically regarding kindergarten.
或perhaps to not diversify their teaching approach.
however， most of these Chinese kindergartens do not accept E.M. students.
this is a prevalent mindset among Chinese parents and kindergartens.
我有 certain experiences and have heard of injustices and discriminatory acts.
now these kids are mostly aged four to six. they do not need to be segregated already.
may not be as fluent in Chinese and would prefer English as their main language, but
this goes to show how concentrated the kindergartens are and how reluctant they are to accept EMs.
或，as they usually claim that it's hard to support their learning. But again, they're kids. We should at least give them a chance.
And kindergartens are worried that having E.M. students will lead parents to perceive the school to be of lower quality.
It is absurd, because even in the very first step of education, we have signs of discrimination.
包括，例如，只接收中文申請forms，或 not being able to access Chinese school websites。
and also attending kindergarten interviews conducted only in Chinese, and we could see how this could be really unfair for them because parents, most of the parents.
for example, in the 2017 and 18 school year, over half of the EM children attending kindergarten are concentrated in 77 schools with 60% or more of the student body being EMs.
另一個例子是，香港UNISON和其他NGO serving EMs，繼續收到來自ethnic minority parents，關於不公義的待遇，他們在報名入讀幼稚園時所受到的。
There's evident discrimination in the admission admission process. A lot of E.M. parents I know have struggled with getting their kids into Chinese local kindergartens, perhaps near their home for better accessibility or convenience.
because after all.
因為 primary schools are dependent on kindergartens.
Thank you much. The next one is Mr. Biswa.
And if we already have that in the first step, then how can it work out step by step?
We are locals too and deserve a chance to study together from early stages of our growth, primarily in kindergartens.
所以， in order to improve education not only for EMs but generally too, we must change this way of segregating Chinese and EMs.
because when kids go to primary schools, they are already expected to know how to communicate in Chinese and be able to handle different subjects in Chinese.
It is the EDB's responsibility to make sure kindergartens are following administrative guidelines, which are to be fair and provide adequate support to both Chinese and EMs. Thank you.
The EDB also said that it has never received from parents any views reflecting difficulties in finding kindergarten places for the children.
and that they have only received one complaint in two school years. This shows that EDB is not familiar with the situation, and it is passive in supporting the parents.
政府應該 step up the monitoring and the support measures regards to admission procedures and the admin guidelines which are given to all kindergartens which are under free kindergarten policy.
Yeah, thank you, Mr. Chairman. A lot of deputations today have reiterated the points of language barrier and low education attainment as a major obstacle for integration into society. Yet I'm reading the indifference on the government official representatives here on the faces, and I hope I'm wrong about this.
所以for with starting with kindergarten early integration of ethnic minority students is very important both for the foundation of language and integration. But studies have found out ethnic minority students face discrimination during kindergarten admission and there is lack of supportive environment in.
schools for non-Chinese speaking students. The Office of Ombudsman completed a direct investigation on government support for non-Chinese speaking students in Feb 2019 and highlighted four main areas that needed attention and improvements from the EDB. In terms of support for ethnic minorities applying for kindergarten.
Starting from 2019-2020 year, EDB will have new arrangements for subsidising kindergarten under the free kindergarten scheme. Unison emphasises that apart from being concerned about whether the subsidy amounts will be increased, questions of transparency and accountability should not be overlooked. Otherwise.
Kindergartens to teach non-Chinese students to a lower Chinese level.
schools which are which traditionally admit only non-Chinese speaking students. Thank you.
de facto segregation still exists in former designated schools with over ninety to ninety to eighty to ninety percent of student body who are still ethnic minorities.
服務，通過葉籤，do you have any data on how many EMS have read or go through services or scheme leaflets, or do you really think that these are just numbers on many leaflets which are being published?
Thank you so much. The next one is Miss Kainat. Thank you. Good morning, I'm Asif Kainat, a Hong Kong-born Pakistani, a first-year student at the University of Hong Kong. I would like to bring your attention to the issue of ethnic minorities (EMs) being aware and satisfied in relations to the welfare aspect.
它將只重複非中文支援在小學和中學，其中很多錢被投入，但沒有太大差別。幼兒園的表現指標間接指導學校教低水平的中文給非華裔學生。在《表現指標》的書中。
There is a point under domain four, which states under language ability and under cognitive development, it refers that the mother tongue development of children who are mostly taught in mother tongue language at kindergartens, and kindergartens should not use the same performance indicators to assess children's.
Learning in a second language, since kindergarten applies to the PIs in teaching and in self-school evaluation, EDB should clarify if they are suggesting another performance indicator on language ability of ethnic minority children whose mother tongue is neither English nor Chinese. Such statements actually mislead.
有效措施應被taken to eliminate the de facto racial segregation in public education system. The EDB should review and revise Box Seven and Appendix Three of the applications forms for Primary One allocation system, which indicates that applicant child cannot use Chinese as medium of instruction. While Appendix Three is a list of
在貧窮情況報告 of ethnic minorities 2016，南亞人stood as the largest group at 30.6% of EM population。 many EMs who were consulted indicated that they know about the social welfare department when they apply for comprehensive social security assistance (SSA) or old age allowance。 however， they do not know about
其他服務由社會福利部門提供。我們知道社會福利部門已盡力促進其服務向EMs，透過翻譯資訊及服務小冊子成EM語言，於服務中心及網上提供。但政府的宣傳策略有助。
EMs to raise their awareness of ability to such services. We are really thankful to the government to be taking this pioneer step in publishing leaflets and newsletters to assert their help and services to specific groups. But do you really think that this primary approach really reaches the EMs? None of the families I know have ever got information about.
Thank you, Lisa。啊，the next one is Miss Kerr。
教育、 attainment and personal development. Thank you.
Thank you, thank you, thank you, Kenneth。因為廣東話真係好難學嘅，我。Okay， the next one is Lisa。
for you the narration of these experiences may sound tedious, but for us it is crucial to discuss this because it addresses a detrimental social phenomenon: concentrated poverty.
abilities and because parents aren't sufficiently informed about school selection procedure, these children enter schools with high concentration of ethnic minorities and are deprived of a Chinese language learning environment.
could not effectively reach EMs, which could be the reason of EMs' low awarenesses to the public services. Therefore, I would like the government to enhance their sensitivity on the behaviour and the needs of EMs. Thank you.
當我們談到福利，我們不單單考慮它與財政援助有關，而係社會援助及社區服務。另一個我會想提上日曬的問題是解讀服務。正如EMs當他們接近服務櫃枱及中心時，由社會福利部門運作，他們
seldom offered interpretation services, even though there is communication gap between EMS seeking services on one hand and frontline staff providing the services on the other hand. It was suggested that the frontline staff of social welfare department should proactively find out the interpretation services which are required.
因為唔係廣東話，I would like to say that it is better to use sometimes of like social welfare department to look for interpretation services rather than using and understanding the concern raised by ethnic minorities over and over again. For EMS who can speak English but not Chinese, frontline staff of government department
appear to have impression that these EMS do not really need interpretation services. However, ethnic minorities sometimes feel that the government departments do not even speak English quite well and are not able to understand their English. This has seriously affected the quality and adequacy of service provided. Furthermore,
There is a tendency of frontline staff or try to avoid this language barrier by asking the EMS to go to another section of the department. So this way, the service users are rotated between the departments and centres without any actual assistance. How can the government assure that this doesn't happen in the community and services are well provided upon request? To conclude, apart
Apart from the language barriers, low awareness and another reason for the low utilisation by the government services by EMs, many EMs are not aware of their rights to use public services or do not have any idea about using public services. Discussion with EMs and non-EM stakeholders also revealed that publicity of government services through established channels.
I am Nisa, a year two student of HKU. I want to talk about segregation because it is an experience that my community is familiar with. We are ethnic, religious and cultural minorities trying to navigate a society that doesn't really know us, despite being a part of Hong Kong's historical fabric for decades. Although I wish to replace.
The word segregation with integration, it does not shed light on the realities, reality of inequalities perpetuated by the existing systematic discrimination. It is often claimed that ethnic minorities prefer certain schools or enter certain occupations because they want to associate with people of their own race, but
但什麼 people fail to realise is that it is rather a byproduct of segregation practice intentionally and unintentionally on Chinese and ethnic minorities by different parties, including the government and schools. It is a question of accessibility: whether these spaces are made welcoming to ethnic minorities in the first place. Let's consider.
this cycle of discrimination. An ethnic minority parent may want to enrol their children in a Chinese kindergarten, but the school may dissuade them from applying, reject their applications, or group all ethnic minorities minority children in PM classes, separated from Chinese children in AM classes. Later on, because of their poor Chinese.
嗯。
Thank you very much.
嗯，thank you.
在2017，只有28名候選人。
我係教Easy Chinese喺我12年嘅primary和secondary school。
The real problem is that even if we are willing willing to learn Chinese, the current education system does not allow us to do so.
Let's not let our young talents who have major potential to thrive in the future to leave Hong Kong. Thank you so much.
Thank you much. So so touching. The government have many question to answer. The next one is, see.
大家好，我叫Nerpreet，我而家喺香港科技大學讀緊商科。我喺香港土生土長。
The civil service bureau is responding to the problem of limited employment of ethnic minorities in the government without actually fully understanding the situation of the Chinese education.
The things that I learned in secondary school were way easier than what I learned in primary school. When we're still learning, oh, like okay, okay，噉樣啦，哦，Okay，我唔噉樣。Then how are we supposed to be fluent in Chinese?
So, I would like to request for changes in the way Chinese is taught. More importantly, we need to have reasonable required level of Chinese proficiency, taking into account the situation and current education system.
而將LPRS降至CREUC Level One，可能看似一個顯著的讓步，但現實是，很少亞裔學生能達成這個結果，這等於HKDSE Chinese考試的Level Four。
which are three per cent of all non-Chinese speaking students sitting the HKDSE Chinese examination attained level three or above in Chinese subject, compared to fifty six per cent of all day school students attaining the same grades. So who is actually benefiting from this policy change?
我通常畀啲本地人讚，哇！你真係好叻啊！你識講中文同埋英文，你一定會好容易揾到一份好工啦。But they don't know that it is not really the case, as the ethnic minorities do not have the level of Chinese proficiency required in Hong Kong.
even in mainstream schools, the education curriculum and schools cannot adequately cater to their needs. Often, pull-out lessons that were intended to help boost students Chinese abilities or subject performance become a form of segregation when these classes are designed with no time frame for bridge over in sight. While this
fosters cultural insensitivity for all parties involved. It also influences ethnic minority students' future prospects. Their lower Chinese abilities and how their colleagues and employers perceive them affects their admittance to well-paying jobs and leadership positions. Their limited social capital restricts their economic mobility.
Statistic from Hong Kong Poverty Situation Report on Ems revealed that in two thousand sixteen, before policy intervention, there were twenty two four hundred poor em households and forty nine four hundred poor ems with a poverty rate of nineteen point four percent. Overall, the poverty rate of South Asians when compared to the overall population.
是19.9% higher。This pattern of poverty among EMs is unfortunately of no surprise, because it has persisted over generations. The existence of racial segregation and resulting social and economic inequalities produces racially concentrated poverty, which impacts job accessibility as.
This grossly affects our choices for post-secondary and careers we choose. Even if we get to university level, seventy percent of secondary courses are in Chinese. What if we needed that course for the job we always wanted? We're not able to pursue the careers which we desire simply because of our Chinese level.
作為 local 香港人。
Thank you. Sit. We are Hongkongers.
Thank you very much. The next one is.
once entering the working world, the current Chinese education policy does not give ethnic minorities adequate Chinese ability to use the language professionally.
They don't understand why ethnic minorities are also Hongkongers, because their imagination of a Hongkonger has always been people of Chinese ethnicity and Chinese-speaking.
however, even though I may consider myself as a Hong Konger, other people may not feel the same, so I have to push myself very far to make myself seem local, and it's not easy.
因為 many of you may not have had the experience of growing up with us as peers, you may not understand us. People in general are unfamiliar with ethnic minorities and their struggle.
Because there's no integration policy and no action from the government to desegregate schools, we ethnic minority students have to keep proving our localness again and again. Even though Hong Kong is where I grew up.
因為社會資本有好多與僱主認知、working opportunities，和甚至關乎福利的關鍵資訊有關。阻止教育內的分離，和一個適當的中文課程，會有助於緩解貧窮。謝謝。
my experience shows that it is indeed possible for Chinese and ethnic minorities to integrate at a personal and social level, and it would have been a lot easier for us if Chinese and non-Chinese students had been learning and working together from the very beginning.
The GCSE Chinese qualification receives neither recognition nor practical use in a professional work setting, and this severely limits the type of work that ethnic minorities can get, and social and professional network that we can gain, and the kind of information and opportunities that we can get.
至少，佢哋集中喺77間學校，而約40%嘅所有ethnic minority兒童 attend primary and secondary education，都集中喺13和9間學校，respectively。所有呢間學校都有學生體， consist of more than 60% ethnic minorities as a majority。
Good morning, everyone. My name is Siddhartha. I am currently a student at the Hong Kong University of Science and Technology, and I would like to share with you all how general segregation in society and ineffective Chinese education for ethnic minorities limit upward mobility for Hong Kong EMs.
as soon as ethnic minorities enter primary and secondary education, we see the divide between locals and locals. How the system separates Chinese from non-Chinese. As a proof of concept, how many of you, as government officials, have ever had the experience of a classmate going through Eid or Ramadan?
many are choosing to leave Hong Kong as they do not see a future for themselves here in the work field. As an ageing society, Hong Kong is losing the diverse talent pool to other countries. I acknowledge the efforts of the government for lowering the Chinese language requirements for some civil service positions. Unfortunately.
The problem starts at kindergarten and continues into our working lives. This segregation starts early on in kindergarten, where kindergartens tend to have a stigma against EM children, starting to put them in separate classes or rejecting their applications based on race. Just over the past two years, we see that over half of all ethnic minority children attending kindergarten.
長。
好。
since E.M. students.
但what about our language needs?
呢個係哈啤巴。
Thank you, chairperson. Good morning. I'm Habiba, born and raised in Hong Kong.
Has the EDB considered the needs of EM students, while also Hong Kongers, in terms of teaching Chinese, teaching the language and curriculum content?
suggest a highly negative perception of EM students' language acquisition abilities and competencies. Schools and teachers have very low expectations of their Chinese learning abilities.
我會想帶領您的 urgent 注意到， ineffective 教育支援措施 for the Chinese learning of ethnic minority students that may be linked to the creation of poverty in Hong Kong.
now lastly, according to Chief Executive Carrie Lam's 2017 policy address, Chinese history has been introduced as an independent compulsory subject for the junior secondary level.
Now, firstly, the current Chinese language curriculum used to teach Chinese to EM children is too easy. The fact that the curriculum remains unchanged despite the introduction of Chinese language curriculum second language framework.
Are and will I will be facing difficulties learning the subject? The EDB needs to address this issue with concrete and workable solutions. The government again has failed in providing support to EM students' Chinese learning.
therefore there should be a thorough review considering the scheme being in its fifth year of implementation and doctor reports relay that the curriculum is no different from the approach taken prior to the introduction of learning framework and that nothing has changed.
Our multilingual ability shows that we are willing and more than capable to learn, just like our Chinese counterparts. However, with inadequate support from the EDB, the government has failed yet again in providing effective support to E.M. children's Chinese learning.
Many ethnic minorities and Chinese are meeting for the first time once they reach university or even the workplace, and they tend to divide themselves according to race. I myself, I join my hall society, Sunjong or XCO, and organise very local social events, including orientation camps, to get involved in campus life because I myself consider myself.
The government needs to recognise the framework has failed to support EM students learn Chinese learning. Secondly, when taught a lower level of Chinese not on par with their Chinese peers, EM children in mainstream public schools suffer in their ability to master other subjects taught in Chinese.
This is more challenging when Chinese is taught in Putonghua as a medium of instruction for Chinese, a third or even a fourth language for many EM students. Hong Kong's policy on language education is to enhance the trilingual ability of the students, which is based on the assumption that Cantonese is the mother.
The reality is that it's very difficult to alleviate the current poverty situation, as it is near to impossible to function effectively in the workplace without a high level of Chinese competency in Hong Kong. Thank you.
Now, low Chinese proficiency ultimately hinders our future pathways, whether in our career pathway or employment prospects. Most jobs these days require reading and writing Chinese. Some even ask for Putonghua proficiency, even though it's not a genuine occupational requirement.
Thank you，下Biba。啊，下一位係嚟自香港社會工作者總工會陳紅秀女士。係，誒，局長、各位官員，你哋好啊！我係香港社會工作者總工會，噉我哋一直都跟進緊咧，致力更新綜合就業援助計劃，即係IEPS嘅服務發展嘅。咁當政府咧今日。
講話要滅貧嘅時候咧，咁但係政府二十幾年嚟咧，一直都冇規劃、冇時間表，亦都冇認真檢視過點樣好好發展一個IEPS嘅服務嘅。咁真正係為就業有困難嘅失業中年人士提供一啲人性化就業服務啊！咁其實呢個計劃咧係由社署一九九九年開始推出，接嚟更新計劃。
開始去到而家已經二十年㗎啦。喺二零零三年咧，就外判咗畀社福機構去營辦噉，而當中都運作十六年㗎啦。但係到今日咧，仍然係未被常規化嘅。咁其實I.P.S.本身咧用社福母嘅概念，就希望咧係可以誒重入個案啦、小組工作啦、細工作咧，係協助失活嘅。
失業嘅中年人士咧，係揾到工嘅，噉就唔係好似勞工處噉樣咧，人肉轉介機器噉樣做到嘅。咁當然仲需要有政府嘅政策配合啦，增加啲可以畀一啲學歷唔高啦、技能唔多啦、體能或健康欠佳嘅人士去揾工嘅。咁甚至乎亦都要政府配合咧，係改變一啲嘅僱主嘅。
平庸心態同埋憂慮咧，係甚至乎學習台灣噉樣制定一啲政策，由政府大頭咧聘用一啲一下有限制，但係仍有工作能力嘅人士，就唔係喺度叫咧，好似頭先第一節噉樣咧，叫話王者咧去揾啊勞工處咧，就去揾工噉就得㗎。嗰啲係解決唔到問題嘅。一陣間都可能我會超時去講一講現實嘅實際。
第環嘅點解咁多人揾唔到工噉，所以就無論你推出咩政策，如果政府唔係做唔到嘢啊，咁所以都請局長一陣間咧都為第一節王者佢嘅頭先你嘅刻薄言論咧，唔該你致歉或者道歉啊，因為而家王者爺喺出邊咧係好難過噉樣喊緊。作為曾經係社工嘅局長，希望你都認真地思考，你需唔需要認真落地瞭解民間疾苦啦？
噉我繼續講翻關於IUBS嘅計劃啦嚇。咁本身咧，成個計劃咧，其實一直都去到舊年先開始正式有規定有社工嘅存在嘅。咁其實過往呢十六年嚟咧，其實每兩至三年就投標一次，當中係嚴重嘅人手流失。我哋喺舊年咧收集咗二十三間嘅營運單位嘅問卷喺。
喺二零一五年至二零一七年咧，有四十九percent嘅社工流失，非社工嘅職級咧有一百一十個percent流失。去到二零一七年至二零一八年，個計劃進行一半咋，已經有二十八個percent社工已經走咗啦。咁成個計劃不斷有人走，不斷有人走嘅情況之下，究竟連社工自嗰啲員工即係協助嚟揾工？
比較慳咯。
都係誒。
去佢班去比較平嘅，其實都唔平嘅。
誒，有時會攞到學校嘅嗰啲誒。
大概就活到兩個月左右咯，但係呢個價就係已經。
誒而家佢補習嘅就係千五蚊到二千蚊嘅。
誒，因為而家都誒跟唔到小朋友嘅功課啦，誒。
誒，例如學校有啲小提琴班啦，都要千二蚊，誒，大概係八堂嘅。
咁如果係誒要考試啊，或者測驗就要加堂，會更加貴啲。
阿花住喺天水圍嘅，有一個小朋友而家誒讀緊嗯四年級嘅。
可以學到近近六個月咯噉樣，因為而家小朋友嘅誒英文係比較差嘅，所以要喺出邊補習。
咁而家係收收得好便嘅，係六百蚊嘅，係比較平。但係而家喺屋企係真係冇錢誒買琴畀小朋友練習咯，誒所以對小朋友都有啲阻礙啊！
但係佢都唔想，但係我都想畀佢學到佢想學嘅嘢咯。佢而家喺出邊學緊鋼琴啦，誒而家嗰邊就要學費減免畀低收入家庭嘅。
工嘅員工都自身不保嘅時候，點樣去幫助其他有就業困難同埋限制人揾工咧？呢一度我都想局長爭講講成個服務嘅發展方向同埋個計劃啦。咁另外啦，我而家就要開始講一講有六大類別，點解去揾勞工署揾固原在，同埋覺得揾唔到工呢？啲都係要係政府正視。如果你解
解決到啲嘅問題嘅話咧，其實佢仍然咧係揾唔到工嘅，或者亦都係滅唔到貧嘅。包括有一啲係長期作為家庭嘅照顧者，佢哋係距離呢個誒社會已經距離咗好耐，但係由於佢哋一路無私嘅付出照顧家人咧，其實係需要有人去協助佢哋明白點樣慢慢轉換個身份，點樣。
重新從頭社會，我舉個簡單前線童工嘅例子，有兩母女，本身個女孩就係一個隱蔽青年，一路去到十八歲都唔肯揾工，去到廿一歲廿歲都繼續唔肯揾工。媽媽單親咗好耐，照顧好耐，亦都唔冇能力去揾工，直至到有童工同個媽媽好好地溝通，講翻畀佢聽，其實工作。
嘅意義或者當中對女兒嘅影響，慢慢慢慢行出第一步，去面對翻佢過往嘅傷痛、過往嘅成長嘅困難，開始願意去揾工作，亦都成功地透過童工同僱主嘅合商，增加僱主聘用一啲可能長期冇嘢做過、冇工作經驗嘅人士，佢終於翻到第。
份工，當佢翻到第一份工之後，佢個女咧就開始望住呢個勤力工作嘅媽媽，開始就喐動啦。佢開始願意向呢個集資上邁進，係嘗試做一啲嘅展示清潔課程。之後亦都係喺Angelo度咧做一啲實習嘅工作，而家已經係全職工作。其實呢啲例子都係講緊咧，成個就業服務唔係純。
在抌錢，或者增加啲咩勞工處啊，或者係其他嘢，而係講緊係需要人性化嘅同工資，包括都有好多中年轉業嘅人士。其實佢哋唔係唔想揾工，亦都係一樣面對緊。其實佢哋過往嘅技能不能再使用，而當家亦都冇足夠嘅工種係畀佢哋去做。
來來去就係保安啦、清潔啦，而售貨員都唔請佢哋，或者有啲倉務都嫌佢年紀大，何況講緊五十幾歲至六十幾歲嘅人士咧？我都想問羅局長，究竟你即時諗到有啲咩工種係適合呢啲學歷低啦、工作技能唔夠啦、誒年紀大啦，亦都唔係大到六廿幾歲，我當五廿幾。
似六啊幾歲嘅人士啦，身體健康狀況亦都可能欠佳啦。呢啲人士究竟有咩工種啱佢哋咧？咁其實過往同工真係要花好多心機、好多努力，係幫助佢哋明白咩工都試下啦。因為多個工好過你左中門啦，中門嘅錢真係唔夠使。但係當中要用嘅時間要有幾多咧？但係唔係冇成效，不過真。
係需要政府抌資源同埋有規劃，亦都需要同工建立一個好好嘅就業發展服務嘅配套同埋發展方向。呢一度都好希望羅總音回應下，究竟點樣去為呢個服務長遠嘅發展係去計劃嘅。唔該。好，因為我仲有幾位朋友咧，我哋要把握時間啦，因為呢一節嘅時間有限。接住落嚟係黃花女士。
哦。
喺香港。
誒有。
誒，為咗小朋友嘅成績。
但係屋企都係唔夠錢畀佢去學。
而家啲功夫都係越嚟越凌，越嚟越難嘅。
都有摩擦，所以都係幫唔到小朋友睇功課。
間中都要同佢跟緊跟緊啲功課，但係。
多謝你。接住落嚟係啊，對呢對呢，one is沙馬，係，thank you very much。
誒，小朋友都想，嗯，同誒小朋友都有同我講過，佢想學其他嘅課外活動啦，想學其他運動啦。
所以都會有畀小朋友喺出邊補習嘅，但係唯有就係減少其他嘅家庭開支咯。
都好似係話誒，每個月都有睇下嗰啲誒煤氣費單啦、電費單啦、水費單嗰啲咯。如果係太貴嘅，畀唔到錢嘅都唯有係拖住先嘅。
要量力而為嘅，誒，希望政府能夠資助小朋友發展佢上學嘅嘢，因為而家係誒啲教育唔同咗啊嘛。
見家長嗰時，你老師都會同我講：誒小朋友嘅誒成績誒退步咗啦，就會問我有冇畀小朋小朋友喺出邊補習，都會畀啲壓力畀我啲家長咯。
唔係使到書，要發展喺其他方面，所以希望政府考慮到唔同嘅資助模式，幫助小朋友發展，誒簡稱基層家庭負擔。各位，謝謝你阿花。誒小朋友聽你解釋話，可能屋企唔夠錢嘅時間，佢明唔明白㗎？
Thank you, chairperson. Good afternoon, everyone. I'm Salma, born and raised in Hong Kong. I would like to touch upon the employment of ethnic minorities within the government and how its method of recruitment, with regards to Chinese language proficiency requirements (LPRs), may be linked to the creation of poverty.
We're surely capable of doing more.
所以，when will the government release the results?
adequate support language support in the education system.
Thank you much。誒，下下一位係嚟自。
但 why 應該我們 only  be  limited  to  disciplined  services?
ultimately， this hinders our upward social mobility.
Despite being qualified for civil service positions, we fall behind our counterparts due to Chinese language ability.
for instance, police constable, police communication liaison assistant, and some positions in the correctional services department.
providing us opportunities to climb up the social ladder will alleviate by far the current poverty situation in Hong Kong. Thank you.
Unfortunately, the government is being selective, as it is making outstanding efforts to encourage ethnic minorities to consider a career in the disciplined forces.
Clearly, the Steering Committee on Ethnic Minority Affairs set up in two thousand and eighteen should thoroughly review the entry requirements relating to Chinese proficiency for all grades of the civil service.
The civil service needs to be diverse and inclusive at all levels. Drawing from different backgrounds and experience will ensure diversity of thought, increase innovation and prevent cultural disconnect.
ethnic minority representation in the civil service should increase. However, there are no statistical figures on the percentage employment of ethnic minorities within the civil service released.
The government, due to the current LPR Chinese LPR of its civil service positions, is losing a diversified and talented pool of individuals who are more qualified and capable than believed to be.
According to two thousand and eighteen policy address, it has been stated that fifty three civil service grades have lowered or will lower their Chinese LPRs. Surprisingly, these mostly include positions in the disciplined services only.
The current Chinese LPRs for most grades and entry ranks within the civil service are to obtain at least level one in use of Chinese in the Common Recruitment Exam (CRE). However, most ethnic minorities are unable to attain this level of Chinese proficiency due to the.
觀塘兒童權利關注咗何如英女士。
誒，我我負責就接送小朋友啦， leftover車費咧就。
嘅問題咯，唔該曬，唔該曬。接住落嚟係李紅女士，嚟自觀塘關注兒童貧窮小組。嗯。
同區安泰村每月租金咧就一千幾蚊，小朋友咧就多咁有資源，九龍灣幾村嗰度翻學咧就坐車就就難為就要兩個鐘，誒送一個鐘接一個鐘，佢又多咁誒半日班啦。
係誒唔該，主席。咁其實誒喺香港啦，咁五個兒童一個窮咧，咁都誒唔係講，即係都講咗好耐㗎啦。噉就其實誒講緊呢幾年啦，咁特別係今年啦，兒童貧窮率咧其實係升咗嘅。咁其實基層兒童無論喺健康，講緊佢哋過輕過重，或者學習發展，其實都係。
係有滯後嘅情況，咁跨代問誒貧窮嘅問題噉樣一路都係延續緊。咁而誒兒童貧窮問題，我諗都講咗好多年啦。咁其實誒我都相信政府就會總係會回應啊。依家有唔同嘅政策支援緊，但係其實我哋每次講就係講緊就係呢啲政策好零散，好多基層。
小朋友其實係接觸唔到，而講緊嗰個內容同埋金額都唔足夠嘅。咁所以咧，我誒今日都想講下唔同政策嘅不足，都希望咧政府係可以回應嘅。噉就誒講咗兒童發展基金先啦，咁都係誒勞福局一個誒，即係都會成日攞出嚟講嘅計劃啦。噉佢由二零零八年開始。
十年嚟，其實佢只不過幫咗一萬七千個嘅小朋友。咁十年內都只不過係有十分一嘅基層小朋友參與過。講緊儲兩年錢，等於就要求小朋友一年用曬。咁其實係誒唔係一個長遠支援緊小朋友發展嘅一個計劃。咁而好多家長其實都反映咧。
其實嗰個限制好大，其實可能小朋友根本就一路都冇參加啲咩課外活動，突然之間可能要佢一年用一筆錢咁去參加一個新嘅活動咧，其實又唔夠，即係唔即係可能學一年咁唔學落去，其實係冇乜用嘅。咁誒，其實我哋見翻啦，之前立法會都有一個研究，其實講緊新界。
波個兒童培育共同儲蓄計劃啦，咁其實係由小朋友一齣世去到十二歲咧，噉樣都係誒家長儲錢噉樣，政府再去做一啲配對啦。咁個儲蓄限額咧係可以去到大概五萬蚊啦上限。咁其實當小朋友真係講緊學習或者醫療嗰陣時有需要嘅時候咧，佢係可以攞。
攞出嚟用咧，咁其實係會畀香港呢一個兒童發展基金咧係全面好多。咁同埋亦都有家長反映過，其實有小朋友畀學校揀中噉樣可以去參加一啲比賽啦。但係其實佢比唔起，即係因為要去誒內地比賽或者係誒要交一啲考試費啊，比賽。
袋錢咧，其實佢哋畀唔起啊，噉就變咗小朋友冇咗呢一個機會。咁所以其實如果有一筆錢咧，係畀小朋友講緊，佢有需要醫療又好、學習又好，可以攞出去用咧，其實可以減少小朋友冇咗呢啲機會嘅損失。咁而再啲家庭津貼都講咗好耐㗎啦，咁又係另一個政府話解決跨誒跨代。
貧窮嘅問題啦，其實講緊依家個兒童津貼都係唔夠十五個percent嘅基層兒童拎到，咁而過往一路講緊可唔可以所有誒攞緊書簿津貼嘅學生都有呢一筆津貼啊？咁勞福局同埋教育局咧，其實都係不斷向我哋推波噉樣，依個係教育局誒學生資助係教育局，跟住再啲家庭津貼就係勞福局。
咁其實到咗依家都係未回應到我哋嘅，咁誒係啦。咁而誒學生資助眾門其實都冇時間去講啦。咁其實我好想講嘅咧，就係其實政府就算定立咗貧窮線之後咧，其實係唔代表係處理緊一啲貧窮問題嘅。咁而兒童事務委員會好似啊，依家成立咗，畀咗個希望我。
哋咧，原來發現半年先至開會一次噉係啦。咁所以我哋希望咧，今日政府咧都係可以係回應我哋係真係有一個真心處理兒童貧窮嘅問題，去定立翻一個減少兒童貧窮嘅目標，同埋咧係誒響扶貧委員會或者兒童事務委員會當中咧，係真係有個小組係真係處理緊兒童貧窮。
由於咧。
一定就要要睇私家醫生，所以呢。
因為小朋友，我所以我喺呢度咧就希望咧小朋友咧。
兒童平常目標啦，建立小組處理兒童問題啦，多謝。
多謝你。接住落嚟係嚟自觀塘關心兒童貧窮小組廖春花女士。
中小學嘅時候咧，增長數倍以上嘅，但係好遺憾，政府一直漠視小朋友升中後嘅各項需要。
比如交通費方面，十二歲乘坐巴士就無法享受半價優惠，小巴更係一直以來都冇法享受半價。
仲有基層家庭小朋友嘅五線增貼，喺小朋友升中後也無法享受呢啲各項雜費嘅增長，係畀我哋嘅家庭帶來沉重嘅經濟壓力。
啲少少家庭咧，小朋友咧，學學習咧同醫療咧開支大咧，平日小朋友想買書啊，或者補補習功夫啊，都冇錢畀佢補啦。買買新衫就更加唔談啦。成日咧就執埋嗰啲親戚朋友啊，嗰啲舊衫啊畀小朋友著啦。
喺呢度，我懇請局長、各位議員，正視中學生嘅需求，讓學童喺十二歲後乘坐巴士也可享受半價優惠；而基層家庭小朋友嘅五線津貼，喺小朋友升中後又可以一直存續。
最後，我希望設立真正嘅兒童津貼，因為我嘅家庭雖然有申請低津，但係我先生係從事散工工作，其實都幾惶恐，唔知佢幾時會失業。一失業咧，呢啲所有福利都冇曬啦。
一個月咧，大約就要一千，接近一千蚊啦。精誒，經濟壓力就好大啦。加上小朋友半夜班咧，我自己又翻唔到工啦。小朋友咧又年紀細啦，又容易得病啦。之前咧就犯過咩誒肺炎啦，睇一次私家醫生咧就要誒三百至四百蚊。
家庭低收入家庭咧，好似我啲咁低嘅收入咧，就每次睇小朋友睇醫生咧，就冇冇錢畀佢睇私家醫生啦，就要去揾嗰啲親戚啊朋友啊先借住先啦，就等第二個月我先出咗糧咧，先先畀翻畀翻嗰啲錢人哋啦。
好，大家好。我啊，我屋企係住觀塘區，一家三口咧，有一個女讀誒，有一個女咧讀K三。先生咧年紀大，就難揾工，而家咧就做緊誒倉務員，每每個月嘅收入咧就大約一萬二千一萬二千蚊。我哋咧上年就報去啱啱誒觀。
阿女咧又試過發過一次玫瑰疹啦。誒由他私家咧，如果如果拍誒拍誒公立醫院咧，就要等可樂啦。但小朋友咧就嗰啲病咧就係唔等得嘅。加上我小朋友咧又有嗰啲殘痘症啦，就唔可以去誒去藥房啊嚟買嗰啲齊齊嗰啲藥畀佢食喎，就一定要變。
誒希望咧，希望小朋友咧就同長者一樣啦，可以有醫療券啦，小朋友有病咧可以用啦，而家開始資助咧，可以從幼兒園開始提供啦，減輕我哋低收入家庭嘅誒負擔啦。誒兒童貧窮嘅問題咧就越嚟越嚴重啦，希望政府咧能誒設定減少貧。
各位午安，我叫廖春花，住喺牛頭角彩福村。我有三個小朋友啦，一個現就讀緊中學嘅，一個今年九月份升讀中學，另一個讀緊小二。眾所周知，小朋友升讀中學校各項費用嘅支出係比小朋友就讀。
人哋冇。
希望政府設立專門嘅扶貧專責小組，減少貧窮兒童嘅數目。多謝各位。
之後，呃，完全康復後，我哋三個都都一個多月之後才完全好翻。其實真係，誒，好幸福㗎。
多謝你。接住落嚟係萬靈雲女士，嚟自呢個嘅關注兒童政策組。嗯，大家好。
誒，誰知道誒？翻到屋企睇埋醫生之後咧，醫生話你唔可以留院啦，話要係誒要做咩啊？要係。
嗯，我是觀塘的街坊啊，我有兩個小朋友，一個誒誒，大大女兒就讀小學二年級啦，小的就讀幼兒園開灣的。
同埋咧，我老公當時咧又話：，邊個讓你去睇睇睇醫生啊？話睇醫生真係好貴，發燒發燒還要去買啲藥，再給他試算咯。真係我都唔知唔知點講呢樣嘢。
你我係大陸人嚟嘅，我呢度嘅英文真係我真係講唔定，我都係一路學，自己一路學，一路交埋佢嘅，真係我都覺得有啲時候當我朝早我唔起好晏起身咧，真係我都覺得我自己，誒。
第二天早上嘅七點多了，就係我有每住一個髮間小個，兩個都發間小個，每每個一個小朋友同埋，呃，每個三個要要報住，兩個都係發燒，真係捱到一個通宵。到時咧，真的我覺得我好幸福啊！真係一個人都沒有得幫手幫到手啊！
我咧就是，誒誒，我老公呢就是，誒誒，做保安啦，誒，他就要翻十二個鍾嘅，誒，在晚宅啦，也要來回翻到廣場都要兩個鍾嘅，加埋加加埋埋都十四個鍾，就係話，誒，在家裏所有的事情咧，他就會幫唔到手啦，都係我一個人。
那麼，誒，平時咧就係買菜啦、煮飯啦、接小孩啦、做功課啦，都係我自己個一個人在做。但係平常咧，如果小朋友健健康康咧就O K嘅。但係咧，如果係小朋友一病咧，一個病係搞個病嘅。就像我去，誒，今年今年初初嗰時咧，我個細女係就感染了嗰個腸炎嘅，佢咧。
又惡又又又發燒嘅，完全都係食唔到嘢。但係咧，我又唔捨得出私家睇喎，就去誒去誒就佢，佢同藥房買啲藥啦，買啲藥噉樣食啦，都係冇好，一陣一拖拖咗幾日，最後咧又入買個大藥，呢只大藥一發燒發到三廿幾度，誒我都唔知。
誒唔知點搞啦，就係誒帶佢去去聯合醫院啦。去到聯合醫院之後，誒我就係帶埋個細個，誒，喺晚上喺九點鐘幾九點九點鐘嗰啲都到誒聯合醫院等等等。結果咧就係只有，誰知道，係只有兩個醫生喺度抬住嘅。誒，等到抬埋醫生已經好。
誒到後來翻到屋企之後，又入埋屋，入埋屋我就喺我自己都並埋，誒家長買埋我的三個東買好，完全好翻。翻到屋企又要清理嗰啲又屙又嘔啲嘢啦，又要玩具啦、被子啦，全部都要洗，全部都要洗過。全部洗埋之後，我自己又並埋，並埋。
同埋咧，呢個呢個道理咧，而家就係好難麻煩啦，好難教啦。小孩子咧，又他又唔想做功課，佢同他做功課咧，你又睇埋咧媽咪呢個字呢個字點樣寫啊？你又你又寫緊菜煮緊飯嗰時，睇呢樣嘢嗰樣嘢，你唔睇佢做功課，他就完全真係做唔到，真真係。
小朋友咧，我哋咧，佢哋班裏邊各個小朋友都有在出邊補習嘅。我哋完全係，我我老公一個月一萬兩千幾蚊嘅工資，真係唔夠付唔夠支出嘅，真係冇錢去同他在外邊補習咯。就係係OK，我自己睇到睇到佢做功課，做功課真係呢個。
第三焦點。
即是點啊？誒。
萬女士，多謝你，你哋啊，你嘅意見我哋聽到啦，多謝你。接住落嚟係朱成愛女士，都係嚟自兒童政策關注組。
大了，用這個特長養家餬口，看大陸的歌星、影視明星，就知道個個趁得盆滿缽滿。
增加香港大學和中文大學醫學專業的招生學額，讓更多香港青年學醫做醫生，虛緩虛緩。
方便兒童生疾病可以看私家醫生，控制病情，以免留有後後遺症。二、牙科保健現在是政府資助小學六年，建議政府增加牙科資助到中學三年級。
真發癲嘅，誒，説實話好多時真好想大奎啊！當我那樣剛要做好的時候咧，好多時，誒，要求我，誒，有有幾個社工就同我講，要佢睇精神科醫生。再係我老住自己定居，誒，要去睇醫生嗰時，再係我都唔記得講啊。
大家好，我叫朱成愛，現在住在觀塘區，家裏有兩個小朋友，其中一個讀小學二年級。我今天要爭取的是一，希望政府增加剛出生零歲至十二歲兒童醫療券，比照長者醫療券，每個兒童每年每人至少兩千元。
因為兒童是祖國的花朵，是國家的希望；青少年是國家的棟梁之材。中國近代思想家、政治家、教育家、文學家梁啟超在《少年中國説》一文中有一段至理名言：「少年富則國富，少年強則國強，少年智則國智。」
所以我希望香港政府增加兒童醫療券津貼，讓香港的青少年擁有強健的身體，為香港的繁榮昌盛做貢獻。小朋友從剛出生至三歲之前最容易生病，而且小朋友生病來得及好的也快，一人生病全家人忙碌。雖然，
香港公立醫院醫療體係健全，看病價格便宜，但是公立醫院人手不足，急診室每天爆滿。如果人發高燒三十九度至四十度，上吐下瀉或暈倒、昏迷等非常緊急的病人，可能在一個小時左右能見到相對應的專業醫生。
一般次緊急的病人，則需要六至八個小時才能見到專業醫生。我自己深有體會。去年十月份，我兒子七歲時，有一個晚上十點鐘左右，肚子痛，發高燒四十度，我在家裡趕緊給他吃了退燒藥，到聯合醫院看基基診時，值班醫生一量體温只有三十八。
嗯。
佢。
揾嗰啲誒。
誒，佢唔會要求出街食飯咯。
誒，我個大女咧都好生性嘅。
同埋買鞋咧都會誒買誒。
同埋去誒，就係買買嗰啲成藥食嘅啫。
買幾十蚊對鞋啦，同埋佢病咗咧，佢都唔會睇醫生嘅。
私人嘅補習資料啦，但係佢一個月咧都要成千幾蚊啦，我哋誒。
佢就知道我哋啲錢咧好緊張啦，誒，從來都唔會向我同佢爸爸要求太多嘅。
同埋佢而家咧誒升讀Band One嘅中學咧，佢由小學誒可以考頭幾名嘅，但係而家咧變到誒啲成績跟唔上啦。誒，同埋佢都會主動同我講話想補習英文嘅同埋數學嘅。
香港政府除了建公屋，令香港人民安居樂業外，希望政府停止建造大型建築工程，停止填海造地建公屋，破壞生態。女士，你哋你嘅意見我聽到啦。接住落嚟係嚟自兒兒童權利關注小組謝雙文女士。
點二度，最好等到第二天凌晨六點鐘再見到專業醫生。如果兒童患有慢性病，例如氣管炎、哮喘、鼻敏感、皮膚病等，非常難約見醫生。一般的病見到醫生看來看去都是一樣的急診藥，醫治沒有效果，僅有兩千元一年的醫療。
醫護人員工作壓力。第二大點，希望政府增加小一至中學三年級在校學生課後興趣班的津貼，因為青少年參加興趣班的學習和擁有一門音樂、美術、舞蹈、體育、武術等特長，有利於提升自信心。
有利於培養做事的耐心，有利於培養高雅廉雅的個人氣質，有有利於提高審美能力，有利於提高生活情趣，減小青少年犯罪機會，讓青少年生活工作變得豐富有趣，讓忙碌的學習和工作有一個休閒和放鬆的途徑。
讓每一個學生中小一至中三年級在校學習九年時間，有機會在讀書的學校，每週上一堂音樂、舞蹈、美術、體育等興趣班的課。讓每個中小學生人人平等，有一份政府資助，學有一個的特長，有可能長。
第三大點，希望政府重視來自基層公民的建議和意見。我上網查到，香港現在有大大小小的體育館五百二十個，可是知名的體育運動員我只知道李惠思，可想而知，每一年體育館的維修費和保養費是一大筆開支。建議。
係大家好，我係來自觀塘區嘅街坊。我有兩個小朋友，一個讀中二，一個讀小一。我先生咧係做技工嘅，誒大概一個月就收入兩萬蚊，誒屬於係誒貧窮線下嘅家庭嘅。我哋而家係。
租住劏房啦，每月嘅租金咧，誒六千蚊。其實經濟咧都好緊張嘅，誒。但係我哋申請學生資助嗰度咧，就只可以攞半額咯，書簿津貼咧就好少嘅。誒小朋友咧冇唔善資助啦，學校嗰啲活動咧都冇資助嘅。
誒，但係出邊嗰啲補習費又比較貴啦。誒，我只可以比較誒，畀佢誒去啲社區中心啊，誒補習嗰啲誒平嘅嗰啲英文班啦。數學嗰方面咧，佢就誒嗰啲社區中心就冇嗰啲數學補習班啦，我就需要出去喺外邊。
成立誒。
都好難負擔得到嘅。
一星期就上兩堂。
減少兒童貧窮目標啦。
我有一個仔，依家讀緊六年級。
即係希望政府可以成立嗰啲誒。
誒同埋處理嗰啲成律誒。
成立誒處理兒童嗰啲小組問題啦，誒多謝。
誒，我小朋友咧就比較中意畫畫嘅，特別中意畫素描啦。
誒希望誒可以成立兒童貧窮問題嘅熱雷誒。
所以我都有畀佢去學畫畫，到依家為止，大約佢都學咗七八年啦。
其實咧，畫畫咧，去學畫畫一啲都唔平嘅。誒，一期四堂大約要三百八十蚊啦。
多謝你。接住落嚟係陳華珍女士。誒，大家午安。誒，我叫華珍。誒，住喺天水圍嘅。
資助嗰啲課程嘅津貼啦，令我哋嗰啲喺誒貧窮線邊緣啊嗰啲學生咧，小朋友都可以有咁多嘅支援啊嗰啲啦。
誒一日連續上兩堂啦。點解要連續上兩堂咧？因為咧畫素描咧，如果如果上一堂一個鐘係畫唔到乜嘢嘅，所以要上兩個兩堂咯。
所以咧，我希望政府咧可以改善學生嘅資助制度啦，誒，令所有貧窮線下嘅啲家庭咧可以申請嗰啲全額資助啊，同埋成立嗰啲四份生嘅嗰啲誒。
誒。
又會再考嘅。
誒嚟緊八月份。
同誒。
而且畫畫咧，唔係就係。
升級試嘅已經考咗三年啦。
所以成日都會係留喺天水圍啦。
每年我都會有畀小朋友考。
你哋知唔知咧？其實畫畫都有考升級試嘅喎。
所以大概三百八十蚊，只係學到兩個星期咯。
得就係咁交學費，仲有其他開支嘅，好似文具啦、畫簿啦。
同同埋咧，我哋就會好少會出去食飯啦，同埋好少會出去玩啦。
因為佢哋佢佢哋中心咧有個政策嘅，一次過交四期錢就有九折嘅，所以四期就一千三百六十八蚊啦。
其實嗰啲考試費都好貴嘅，佢會跟住即係你嘅級數越高就加得越多咯。除咗佢要交考試費，中心仲要收埋手續費啦。
但係交學費嗰個月咧，就好影響家庭開支啦。噉我就要諗其他方法去壓縮家庭開支啦，好似就等到街市就嚟收檔嘅時候去買平嘅餸啦。咁噉樣其實係唔係咁有營養嘅？
先請局長。
買到過去畀個仔考咯，嗰次。
咁好彩，畀佢考過咗啦！好，其實都好驚險嘅。
係，其實講緊即係發展興趣，其實係需要好多支出嘅。
咁所以，我哋都會歡迎咧，誒業界咧就住如何喺日後呢個發展嘅服務咧，畀啲意見我哋，嗯。
而對於基層家庭嘅負擔係好重嘅，你哋就話誒學生一人一體藝，咁冇錢點發展一人一體藝咧？
去執個紙皮啦，或者執個木板啦。點知執咗紙皮去嗰度，誒嗰度考試場話唔得。誒好在有間文具鋪開咗，我又。
政府依家冇嘢可以支援到小朋友持續發展，希望有持續性措施可以支援小朋友發展，就好似就唔係好似地區青少年發展資助計劃噉，誒名額不足又係只係嗰個短期措施咧。多謝大家。
仲有跟住考試要租佢個畫架，同中心租每次都要畀一百蚊嘅。誒，記得有次第一次考試啦，就唔係咁有經驗啦。嗰次冇攞到畫架，就打電話同中心嗰啲協商，佢就叫我。
多謝你話真，因為小朋友的確係我哋即係最大嘅希望嚟嘅，即係會用盡我哋嘅力量咧，畀佢能夠即係學到更加多嘅嘢啦，或者即係建立佢未來。多謝你好啊！我哋嘅公聽嘅啊，即係啊，局別人士嘅發言咧，就到此為止。咁先聽聽局長有冇簡短回應啦。另一方面，我哋委員睇下有冇追問嘅。
誒，都多謝主席。誒，今日誒喺呢一節咧，我哋都聽到好多特別有關少數族裔嗰啲誒所面對特別，譬如喺中文嗰個嘅學習嘅問題啦。誒，實際上呢個問題大家都知道喺二零一四年，當誒特區政府就誒都覺得應該要推行中文作為第二語言咧，就開始發展咧。誒，相
相關嗰啲嘅課程啦、工具啦，同埋有關嘅培訓。我亦聽到大家講咧，係關於嗰啲教師嗰啲嘅訓練嗰個問題啦，包括咗點樣去教誒中文作為第二語文，同埋誒點樣去提升佢哋對於誒文化嗰個嘅敏鋭性啦。咁呢啲嘅誒嘅意見咧，我哋都會向教
各方面咧去反映嘅，誒近期我亦都知道咧，教局特別係對於誒幼稚園嗰個嘅學習中文呢個問題咧，係要加把勁。咁呢啲工作咧都喺度進行緊嘅。誒另外咧，社會福利處都會喺今年咧係會開始嘗試咧去誒揾細誒一啲非政府機構啦。
去提供一啲外展嘅服務，希望係能夠接觸到咧少數族裔，幫佢哋咧聯繫到咧現時嘅現有一啲嘅社會服務嘅一啲嘅支援嘅網絡。咁呢個嘅試驗計劃，我哋希望喺今年年底之前咧係可以能夠誒開始誒醖養啦，係喺今個嚟緊呢個財政年度咧去推出嘅。
誒，我哋亦都聽到一啲嘅意見，有關誒呢個喺綜合誒就業支援服務計劃裏頭。咁大家都可能會知道咧，喺誒嚟緊呢一年嘅時間咧，我哋會就住未來嗰個誒綜合誒就業支援計劃裏頭喺綜援嘅制度裏頭咧，點樣去改善同埋將來嗰個運作嘅。
至於喺兒童嗰個方面咧，雖然誒大家都仍然睇到咧，我哋喺不論喺誒學生嘅資助啦，誒喺我哋嘅誒在職家庭資助裏頭咧，都幫到唔少嘅細路。咁當然可能亦都係有啲嘅誒小朋友咧，仍然係所謂流亡資源。不過我哋會係多方面喺個政策上。
陳局長。
同嗰方面嘅關注同聲音啦。
咧去檢視同埋點樣去啊優化佢嘅，多謝主席。
任何嘅改變咧，另外有關即係兒童方面咧。
你二零一八年嗰個報告都係講緊一七年個數字，噉。
公務員裏邊，你哋聘用咗幾多誒少數族裔，尤其是係講緊南亞裔嘅人士咧？
到低過百分之十以下嘅，即係當然係講緊政策介入誒之後啦。咁而家我哋咧仍然係講緊誒百分之十七點五嘅，你有冇一個目標去降低兒童貧窮率咧？
好啊，接住落嚟咧，就我哋嘅委員提問，我哋收到就係張千紅議員同埋陸仲紅議員啊。我哋嘅時間都啊啱啱好嘅啫，噉我哋四分鐘連問連答好嘛。先請張千紅議員。好多謝主席。首先多多謝咁多位團體嚟到啦。誒呢一節我哋聽到比較多少數族裔啦，同埋兒童。
頭先我誒唔好意思，中間咧，我因為有個有關自閉症人士嘅記招，我離開咗。噉我想就住少數族裔嗰度咧，其實佢哋多年嚟咧都係希望誒能夠有啲好啲教育嘅機會啦，然後誒及後佢出去揾工咧，能夠通過工作收。
收入啊，脱離貧窮啦。誒呢方面咧，我聽到啊，頭先阿三華問咧，即係點解咁多年嚟政府唔可以去降低佢嗰個誒中文語言個要求咧？淨係得嗰十三個職係咧，同埋誒有關誒政府究竟嗰十七萬。
呢個數字唔知啊，局長掌唔掌握咧？喺嚟緊，即係政府有冇誒一啲嘅措施係令到誒呢啲小數族裔，我哋講緊係貧窮嘅小數族裔咧，喺香港佢個就業機會，尤其是喺政府聘用嗰度咧，喺政策上會有。
誒，其實多年嚟，我哋兒童嘅貧窮率都唔係即係改善得好多。咁尤其是團體都指出啦，誒，今年個兒童貧窮率咧係比即係我講緊二零一七啦，誒，對於一六嚟講咧，嗰個係誒上升嘅。呢個都係最新嘅數字啊！
喺呢個噉嘅情況底下，誒政府除咗即係嗰個十年先幫到萬幾人嗰個嘅兒童發展基金之外，有咩措施？即係你呢個在職家庭津貼亦都誒飽受批評啦。誒將嗰個工作同誒工作時數同。
兒童津貼掛鈎呢個已經係一個苛政啦，係有咩政策會改善？誒，可以大幅將兒童嘅貧窮率降低。正如即係誒英國曾經做過一啲指標啦，而家蘇格蘭亦都有個指標咧，佢哋話二零三零年咧要將兒童嘅貧窮率咧下降。
誒誒，主席，而家可以提供多啲資料咧，就係喺現時政府嘅公務員嘅職係咧，係誒降低咗佢中文語文嘅能力嘅要求咧，已經係誒五十三個㗎啦。誒，實際上呢個亦都係回應緊喺社會上嗰個嘅聲音啦。誒，不過就住有關公務員裏。
又未必能夠直接對比。
其實都係誒，唔能夠忽視嘅。
嘅，亦都有一啲咧。如果你哋出去補習嘅話咧，都真係幾貴。
但係實際嚟講咧，教育局咧去協助小朋友嘅貧窮問題咧。
咧嗰個殘疾嘅資助，咁同埋呢個小學族裔嗰個資助同樣地，不過我都理解咧，就係今次冇講喺呢個問題咧，會談到嘅。
誒，甚至乎佢包括核下嘅即係學生資助辦事處啦，佢嗰個而家嗰個書簿津貼嘅標準咧，係為人非常舊病嘅，因為金額係少，門檻又嚴。
誒兒童嗰邊有冇誒畀多一分鐘回應啊？誒阿主席就正如喺上一次我都係咁回應嘅啦，喺嗰個所謂扶貧嗰個所謂減貧嘅目標咧，誒現時政府係冇呢個計劃去做嘅。
嘅小朋友，誒跨代貧窮同埋啲少數族裔嘅問題。其實香港嘅貧窮問題咧，即係如果用聯合國嘅標準，香港冇絕對貧窮嘅嚇，不過個相對貧窮咧相當嚴重，因為貧富懸殊好嚴重。誒有一批人咧好有錢。
嘅環境之下咧，佢點樣去裝備自己咧？點樣喺佢成長嘅過程裏邊誒，對自己有信心咧，定立到志向目標咧？我想問嘅一個問題咧，就係我想問下局長咧，係我知道誒呢個話題咧，我係勞福局主主力嘅。
頭係誒請咗幾多不同嘅誒族裔嘅資料咧？因為我哋基本上係冇蒐集呢個嘅嘅資料嘅，咁所以呢個資料係不能夠即係未能夠可以提供，即係等於我諗將二係咪可以開始蒐集咧，局長？因為呢個都係關於誒少數族裔佢哋能唔能夠。
通過政府嘅工作咧，誒得到一個合理嘅收入。誒誒，主席，我我理解公務員事務局係誒會睇呢個問題嘅。誒，因為因為喺好多年前咧，誒，因為過咗條法例有關呢一個種族歧視同埋殘疾歧視之後咧，就好多資料，因為擔心咧就係誒會構成。
係誒，所以歧視嘅成分，因為要先證明咧，呢個資料本身係喺所謂聘用嘅過程係必須嘅資料。咁所以喺誒好多年前咧，啲資料就已經冇噉，所以我諗話張員都知道，就算好似殘疾人士嗰個資料，就係而家佢數會落下降，其中嘅最主要原因咧，就我哋經常冇蒐集緊我哋公務員。
或者我哋第三節同埋第四節，我哋下晝仲有兩節公聽會咧，都係一個好嘅時間嘅聚物。接住落嚟係陸仲紅議員，誒多謝主席，誒都多謝咧咁多位出席嘅團體同埋代表同埋個人人士啊，即係都表達到對貧窮嘅關問題嘅關注。特別我都聽咗好多咧係誒關心即係。
噉啊，因為肥到漏油嘅，噉啊，相對咧有一班嘅人咧就有個相對嘅貧窮，咁再加上咧社會嘅競爭好大啦，咁其實各種嘅需要咧都係需要與時俱進嘅嚇。如果唔係咧，特別係小朋友下一代，佢好難喺呢個咁激烈嘅環境之下咧競爭。
改良嘅工作。
有冇補充，局長？
好唔該曬，誒好，首先我哋再一次感激今日嚟到畀意見嘅咁多嘅朋友。
局長有冇補充？相信我哋甚至呢一節咧未能夠有回應都好咧，我相信第三同埋第四節都有時間。
誒誒，主席，我我相信誒勞工處係應該可以幫到一班咧，有佢需要揾工嘅朋友嘅嚇，多謝主席。
誒政府係咪能夠喺功課輔導嗰方面咧，都提供一個即係最起碼嘅支援同埋配套咧？嚇，唔該，主席。
誒，我哋下我哋跟住之後嗰節嘅公聽會咧，係安排喺兩點鐘喺會議室二係舉行嘅。噉我哋就喺誒晏晝嘅時間咧，我哋會繼續進行我哋第三節公聽會時間。
方面嘅支援，又或者頭先你講話中文好難，又或者甚至乎有好多嘅機會同一個叫做可能係一個融合啊，一個中文嘅學習等等有關嘅，喺羅福嗰個角度有冇嘢可以幫到手？
都會係去加強嗰啲資源咧，係畀一啲譬如特殊教育嘅誒單位咧，係如果當佢有一啲嘅小數族裔嘅時候咧，點樣去誒增強嗰啲嘅學校或者嗰啲幼兒園嗰個支援嘅工作嘅。
啊啊！主席，我想問下誒農福局局長啊，羅博士咧，同教育局局長嗰邊嗰兩個局中間有啲咩協作嘅工作，能夠喺即係跨代貧窮或者兒童貧窮嗰方面有啲工作就係做緊嘅咧？
陳局長，誒誒主席，我會將誒議員嘅意見咧向誒教育局去去反映嘅。誒，我我理解咧，特別喺嗰個嘅書簿津貼嗰個制度裏頭咧，教育局都不時係睇緊現時嗰個嘅制度有冇地方係需要優化。咁呢個意見，我會向佢反映翻。
咁一個就係我最想問咧，就係誒問局長，即係農福局局長同教育局局長喺呢方面咧有啲咩協作嘅工作做緊？同埋咧，我知道政府咧誒比較難去定立一個誒即係滅滅貧嘅目標啊，雖然冇我哋國家咁咁有魄力。咁當然國家嗰個一個絕對貧窮嘅標準。
咁但係，我覺得咧嗰個魄力係要嘅，能唔能夠定一啲咧小朋友嘅一啲喺學習上嘅支援嘅一啲配套嘅標準咧？特別你話誒有兩樣嘢，我聽到好清楚，一個就係誒一生一體藝嗰樣嘢。我知道咧有啲參差，我有時去誒探同學校咧，有啲學校咧佢可能有啲熱心人士啊，有啲言達啊，或者。
佢本身辦團體有錢咧，好平㗎啲活動一係畀啲小朋友差唔多免費咁滯㗎喎。有啲可能咧，誒弱勢啲學校咧，就可能係呢方面嘅活動係少啲嘅。咁呢方面政府點可以支援咧？另外就係誒小朋友功課補習嘅問題，誒未必個家長有時間有能力去照顧細蚊仔嘅功課。
誒誒，主席亦當然咧，大家有誒分工，亦都有合作嘅。咁當然誒喺誒過往裏頭咧，喺關愛基金咧都有唔少嘅項目係針對誒有關學童，特別面對一啲低收入家庭嘅兒童嘅。咁呢個嘅工作誒，我相信將來都會繼續會大家會去協商同埋點樣去。
好，唔該曬。啊誒，最後就我問個短問題啫，因為其實咧就首先誒真係好感激今日好多位嘅朋友，誒少數族裔嘅朋友喺呢一節咧，其實好畀心機去畀問題，我哋希望局長聽到，可唔可以局長講多少少，或者可唔可以承諾一啲嘅，即係起碼畀佢哋誒唔好失望而回啦。喺少數族裔。
誒，我相信頭先誒主席你個問題咧，主要都係針對喺教育嘅嘅環節啦，特別係由幼稚園一路上去中學嗰個學習中文嘅情況。誒，自從二零一四年之後咧，誒教育局呢方面咧不斷都係作出努力。不過我相信大家係需要時間啦。噉係咪能夠做得更加好咧？誒，特別係。
係越早介入，大家都知道係好重要噉，所以喺幼稚園嗰個工作係重要啦。咁誒喺羅福嗰下低咧，我哋社會福利處因為都有其他我哋叫做誒誒，即係啲早期教教育嘅工作嘅噉，所以喺誒今由今年呢呢個財政年度咧嚟緊嚟緊嘅財政年度咧，我哋。